[{"question":"The process 'Amniocentesis' is the withdrawal of amniotic fluid during:","a":"Menopause","b":"Lactation","c":"Gestation","d":"Pregnancy","hint":"Amniotic fluid is secreted by amnion of foetus during pregnancy.","correct":"d"},{"question":"The chemical method of contraception includes:","a":"Jellies only","b":"Creams and foams only","c":"Oral contraceptives only","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which one of the following is tested by the technique of amniocentesis?","a":"Biochemical abnormalities in the foetus.","b":"Errors of metabolism in the foetus.","c":"Chromosomal abnormalities in the foetus.","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is a method for birth control?","a":"IUDs","b":"GIFT","c":"HTF","d":"IVF-ET","hint":"Intra utrine device (Copper-T) inhibit fertilisation and help in birth control.","correct":"a"},{"question":"Identify the characteristics of IUDs. (i) Increase phagocytosis of sperms.  (ii) Releases Cu ions that suppress sperm motility and fertilising capacity of sperms.  (iii) Make the uterus unsuitable for implantation.  (iv) Make the cervix hostile to sperms. (v) Prevent semen from entering the female  reproductive tract.","a":"(i), (ii), (iii), (iv) and (v)","b":"(i), (ii), (iii) and (iv)","c":"(i) and (ii)","d":"(ii), (iii) and (iv)","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Choose the correct statements given below, regarding contraception.  (i) Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP)  during first trimester is generally safe. (ii) Generally chances of conception are nil until mother breast-feeds the infant upto two years.  (iii) Intrauterine devices like copper-T are effective contraceptives.  (iv) Contraception pills may be taken upto one  week after coitus to prevent conception.","a":"(i) and (ii)","b":"(ii) and (iii)","c":"(iii) and (iv)","d":"(i) and (iii)","hint":"Contraceptive pills have to be taken daily for a period of 21 days starting preferably within the first five days of menstrual cycle. It helps in the prevention of conception. As long as the mother breast-feeds the child fully, chances of conception are almost nil only up to a maximum period of six months following parturition.","correct":"d"},{"question":"The success of birth control programmes in  controlling population growth is dependent on:","a":"Use of contraceptives","b":"Tubectomy","c":"Vasectomy","d":"Acceptability of the above by the people","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"World AIDS day is:","a":"December 21","b":"December 1","c":"November 1","d":"June 11","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Hepatitis B is transmitted through:","a":"Blood transfusion","b":"Intimate physical contact","c":"Sexual contact","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Emergency contraceptives are effective if used within:","a":"72 hours of coitus","b":"72 hours of ovulation","c":"72 hours of menstruation","d":"72 hours of implantation","hint":"Emergency contraceptives are effective if used within 72 hours of coitus.","correct":"a"},{"question":"Test-tube babies are produced in a process when:","a":"fertilising egg is removed from the body of the female and fertilised with the husband's sperm outside in vitro culture and then the zygote is transferred back to mother's uterus.","b":"external fertilisation and development in vitro culture till 32 cell stage before putting the embryo back into mother's uterus.","c":"complete development of a baby take place in vitro.","d":"development upto 32 cell stage of embryo takes place and its transplantation in the uterus of a surrogate mother occurs.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Intensely lactating mothers do not generally  conceive due to the","a":"suppression of gonadotropins.","b":"hypersecretion of gonadotropins.","c":"supression of gametic transport.","d":"supression of fertilisation.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Foetal sex can be determined by examining cells from the amniotic fluid by looking:","a":"Barr bodies","b":"Autosomes","c":"Chiasmata","d":"Kinetochore","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Progesterone pill helps in preventing pregnancy  by not allowing:","a":"Ova formation","b":"Fertilisation","c":"Implantation","d":"None of these","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In vitro fertilisation is a technique that involves transfer of which one of the following into the fallopian tube?","a":"Zygote only","b":"Embryo only, upto 8-cell stage.","c":"Either zygote or early embryo upto 8-cell stage.","d":"Embryo of 32-cell stage.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The given figure shows one of the elements releasing intrauterine device. Select the option which shows the correct identification of the device and its feature","a":"CuT: Suppress sperm motility and its fertilising capacity.","b":"Cu7: Make uterus unsuitable for the attachment of blastocysts.","c":"Lippes loop: Protect the users from  contracting AIDS and STDs.","d":"LNG-20: Acts as spermicidal means and decrease the contraceptive efficiency.","hint":"The given figure is that of copper CuT Cuf is a simple copper releasing IUD made of a flexible, \"T\" shaped piece of plastic wrapped with a thin copper containing wire. It helps the uterus and fallopian tubes to produce fluid that kills sperm. This fluid contains white blood cells, copper ions, enzymes, and prostaglandins. Copper ions prevent pregnancy by inhibiting the movement of sperm, because the copper-ion containing fluids are directly toxic to sperm. Even if an aggressive little spermatozoan fertilises an egg, the copper ion laden environment prevents implantation of the fertilised egg. and thus pregnancy.","correct":"a"},{"question":"Reproductive health in society can be improved by:  (i) Introduction of sex education in schools.  (ii) Increased medical assistance.  (iii) Awareness about contraception and STDs.  (iv) Equal opportunities to male and female child. (v) Ban on aminocentesis.  (vi) Encouraging myths and misconceptions,","a":"All of the above","b":"(i), (ii), (iv) and (vi)","c":"(i), (ii), (iii), (iv) and (v)","d":"(ii) and (v)","hint":"Reproductive health in society can be improved by creating awareness among people about various reproduction related aspects and providing facilities and support for building up a reproductively healthy society.","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct.(i) Infertility is the inability to produce viable offsprings due to the defects in the female partner.  (ii) Complete lactation helps in contraception. (iii) Spreading awareness can help in creating a reproductively healthy society.","a":"(ii) only","b":"(i), (ii) and (iii)","c":"(ii) and (iii)","d":"(i) and (iii)","hint":"Infertility is the inability to produce viable offspring due to the defects in female or male partner.","correct":"c"},{"question":"Match column-I with column-II and select the correct answer using the codes given below.  Column-I  Column-II A. Hepatitis B 1. Vitamin E  B. Saheli  II. 7' April, 1948  C. Normal functioning of reproductive  III. CDRI, Lucknow  organs D. World Health  IV. Detection of antibody/  organisation  antigen  E. ELISA technique V. Hepatitis B virus","a":"A-V; B-III; C-I; D-II; E-IV","b":"A-V; B-II; C-I; D-III; E-IV","c":"A-V; B-III; C-IV; D-II; E-I","d":"A-V; B-II; C-IV; D-III; E-I","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following STDs are not completely curable?","a":"Chlamydiasis, gonorrhoea, trichomoniasis","b":"Chancroid, syphilis, genital warts","c":"AIDS, syphilis, hepatitis B","d":"AIDS, genital herpes, hepatitis B","hint":"AIDS, genital herpes and hepatitis B are sexually transmitted diseases which are not completely curable.","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following infections can also be transmitted by sharing of injection needles, surgical instruments, etc., with infected persons, transfusion of blood, or from an infected mother  to the foetus too?","a":"Hepatitis B and HIV","b":"Genital herpes and HIV","c":"Syphilis and Hepatitis B","d":"Chlamydiasis and Trichomoniasis","hint":"Hepatitis B is an infectious disease caused by the hepatitis B virus (HBV) which affects the liver. HIV (human immunodeficiency virus) is a virus that attacks the immune system, the body's natural defense system. Without a strong immune system, the body has trouble fighting off disease. Both the diseases can also be transmitted by sharing of injection needles, surgical instruments, etc., with infected persons, transfusion of blood, or from an infected mother to the foetus too.","correct":"a"},{"question":"'Safe period', a means of birth control is based on:","a":"Ovulation which occurs on the 14th day of menstrual cycle.","b":"Ovum which survives for about 2 days.","c":"Sperms which remain alive for about 3 days.","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Assisted reproductive technologies (ART) includes which of the following statement(s)?","a":"Social awareness programmes to educate people about reproductive health and diseases.","b":"Research organisation working on to produce new and more effective contraceptives for birth control.","c":"A number of special techniques which assist infertile couples to have children","d":"Both (b) and (c)","hint":"Assisted reproductive technologies (ART) include a number of special techniques which assist infertile couples to have children. In-vitro fertilisation is one such technique.","correct":"c"},{"question":"The stage transferred into the uterus after induced fertilisation of ova, in the laboratory is:","a":"Zygote","b":"Embryo at 4 blastomere stage","c":"Embryo at 2 blastomere stage","d":"Morula","hint":"In Intra-Uterine Transfer (IUT), embryo with more than 8-blastomeres stage (morula) is used for transfer into the uterus.","correct":"d"},{"question":"The process, by which transfer of zygote or early embryo (up to 8 blastomeres) into fallopian tube takes places, is called","a":"IVF and ET","b":"ZIFT","c":"GIFT","d":"IUT","hint":"ZIFT (Zygote intra fallopian transfer) is the process in which the zygote or early embryos (with upto 8 blastomeres) is transferred into the fallopian tube.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following statements are correct  for an ideal contraceptive?  (i) It should be user-friendly. (ii) It should be easily available.  (iii) It should be ineffective and reversible with least side effects.  (iv) It should be effective and reversible with least side effects.  (v) It should interfere with the sexual act of the user.","a":"All of these","b":"(i), (ii) and (iii)","c":"(i), (ii) and (iv)","d":"(i), (ii), (iv) and (v)","hint":"An ideal contraceptive should be user- friendly, easily available, effective and reversible with no or least side-effects.","correct":"c"},{"question":"Select the correct match of the techniques given in column-I with its feature given in column-II.  Column-I A. IUT  Column-II  I. Copper-T  B. Birth control  II. Agent to kill spermatozoa  C. Spermicides III. VD or RTI IV. To help infertile couple  D. STD","a":"A-IV; B-III; C-I; D-II","b":"A-IV; B-III; C-II; D-1","c":"A-II; B-IV; C-I; D-III","d":"A-IV; B-1; C-II; D-III","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Identify the incorrect statements and select the correct option.  (i) Birth control pills are likely to cause cardiovascular problems.  (ii) A woman who substitutes or takes the place of the real mother to nurse the embryo is called surrogate mother. (iii) Numerous children have been produced  by in vitro fertilisation but with some  abnormalities.  (iv) Woman plays a key role in the continuity of the family and human species.  (v) Foetal sex determination test should not be banned.","a":"(i) and (ii)","b":"(ii) and (iv)","c":"(iii) and (v)","d":"None of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is not correct about syphilis?","a":"Primary stage of disease shows the appearance of chancre on genitalia and lips.","b":"In quaternary stage of disease, thick pus is  discharged from urinogenital organ.","c":"Secondary stage of disease shows the appearance of multiple lesions on mucous  membrane of lips, mouth and genitalia.","d":"Tertiary stage of disease shows the appearance of gumma on the skin.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Identify the false statement regarding the techniques of contraception.  (i) Tubectomy and vasectomy show many side effects.(ii) Purpose of tubectomy is to prevent formation  of ova. (iii) The most important component of the oral  contraceptive pills is progesterone. (iv) Contraceptive oral pills help in birth control  by preventing ovulation.","a":"(i), (ii) and (iii)","b":"(i) and (ii)","c":"(iii), (iv) and (ii)","d":"(iv) and (ii)","hint":"There are little or no side effects of tubectomy and vasectomy. The purpose of tubectomy and vasectomy is to block the passage of ova and sperm respectively.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Non-gonococcal urethritis is caused by:","a":"Neisseria gonorrhoeae","b":"Chlamydia trachomatis","c":"Treponema pallidum","d":"E. coli","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Recurrence of watery blisters on the genitalia and swollen lymph nodes in the groin are symptoms of:","a":"Genital warts","b":"Genital herpes","c":"Genital lesions","d":"Genital hepatitis","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The most important component of the oral contraceptive pills is:","a":"Progesterone","b":"Growth hormone","c":"Thyroxine","d":"Luteinising hormone","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The diaphragm, cervical cap and vaults are:","a":"Disposable contraceptive devices","b":"Reusable contraceptives","c":"IUDS","d":"Implants","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Birth control pills check ovulation  in female by  inhibiting the secretion of:","a":"Follicle stimulating hormone (FSH)","b":"Luteinising hormone (LH)","c":"Both (a) and (b)","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following ions plays an effective  role in the activity of IUDs?","a":"Iron","b":"Zinc","c":"Copper","d":"Ammonium","hint":"Copperions play an important and effective role in the activity of IUDs. Copper IUDs primarily work by disrupting sperm mobility and damaging sperm so that they are prevented to take part in the process of fertilisation. The increased copper ions in the cervical mucus inhibit the sperm's motility and viability, preventing sperm from traveling through the cervical mucus or destroying it as passes through.","correct":"c"},{"question":"Copper-T is a device that prevents:","a":"Implantation of blastocyst","b":"Ovulation","c":"Fertilisation","d":"Egg maturation","hint":"Copper 'T' is an intrauterine device which prevents the fertilised egg becoming implanted in the wall of the womb.","correct":"a"},{"question":"Contraceptive oral pills help in birth control by:","a":"killing the sperms in uterus.","b":"forming barriers between sperms and ova.","c":"preventing ovulation.","d":"killing the ova.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"'Saheli' is a new oral contraceptive, developed  by:","a":"All Indian Institute of Medical Science","b":"Central Drug Research Institute","c":"Health Care Pvt. Ltd.","d":"Bharat Immunologicals & Biologicals  Corp. Ltd.","hint":"'Saheli'-an oral contraceptive for the females was developed at Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI) in Lucknow, India.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Profuse, yellowish, greenish frothy smelling discharge from vagina is due to infection of:","a":"Treponema pallidum","b":"Chlamydia","c":"Trichomonas vaginallis","d":"Neisseria","hint":"","correct":"c"}]